# MattRalston

blend of bioinformatics and biochemistry

### contact

Matt Ralston 15 Innovation Way Newark, DE 19717

Phone: 302.547.2437 Email: mrals@udel.edu matthewralston.github.io LinkedIn:matthewralston

## bioinformatics

Bowtie, Tophat, BWA Blast, Blat, Clustal Cufflinks, Trinity, Velvet Samtools, Picard, Bedtools DESeg,MACS, Circos

### programming

♥ Ruby/Rails, R Bash, Python, Julia Matlab, ੴEX, Racket MySQL, SQLite Javascript, CSS/HTML

## laboraory

RNA-seq, qRT-PCR Northern & Western Spectrometry, HPLC Immunofluorescence Immunohistochemistry Microscopy, HPLC FACS, GC-MS Mammalian cell culture Anaerobic fermentation

## **summary**

Combines a mechanistic mindset from a B.S. in Biochemistry with M.S. in Bioinformatics to produce and interpret 'omics datasets from Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) reflected by an academic research record. Enjoys research and development, from experimental design to analysis. Offers interdisciplinary expertise for teams of scientists, engineers, and analysts.

## education

2012-2015 **Masters** of Bioinformatics and Computational Biology **3.97** University of Delaware

Assembling Improved Gene Annotations in Clostridium acetobutylicum with

RNA Sequencing.

2008–2012 **Bachelors** of Biochemistry University of Delaware

Minor in Biochemical Engineering, Scholarship, Summer Research Fellowship

# **experience**

2012-Now **DELAWARE BIOTECHNOLOGY INSTITUTE** 

Newark, DE

Graduate Research Assistant

Accomplishments:

- Developed and utilized laboratory and computational workflows for first strand-specific deep RNA-seq and transcriptome assembly in *Clostridia*.
- Built and launched a genome browser for research community.

2010-2012 Center for Translational Cancer Research

Newark, DE

Undergraduate Research Fellow

Investigated the BMP-signaling pathway in colon cancer cells and tissue.

## leadership

2014 Bioinformatic Student Association Newark, DE

President

Organized and led a UNIX and HPC student development workshop.

2013 IGERT Business, Ethics, and Communication Project Newark, DE

Project Manager

Won a proposal for a revision to Fraunhoffer CMB's vaccine production process.

# **publications**

- "Complex and extensive post-transcriptional regulation revealed by integrative proteomic and transcriptomic analysis of metabolite stress response in *Clostridium acetobutylicum*", contributing author. *BMC Genomics*. (2015). Accepted
- "Overexpression of the *L. plantarum* peptidoglycan biosynthesis murA2 gene increases the tolerance of *E. coli* to alcohols and enhances ethanol production", contributing author. *Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology* 98.19 (2014): 8399-8411.
- "The Clostridium small RNome that response to stress: the paradigm and importance of toxic metabolite stress in C. acetobutylicum", contributing author. BMC Genomics. 14.1 (2013): 849.